YOONJOO LEE

voonjoo.lee@kaist.ac.kr | voonjoolee.com

RESEARCH INTEREST

My research interest lies in the intersection of human-computer interaction (HCI) and natural language processing (NLP). I aim to support people to learn from and make sense of dense information (e.g., content in lecture videos and scientific articles) by structuring the information in the context to create adaptive scaffoldings (e.g., QAs, dialogues, explanations) using AI models.

EDUCATION

KAIST Daejeon, Republic of Korea

Ph.D. Candidate in Computer Science. Advisor: Juho Kim

Sep. 2020 – Present

Ewha Womans University Seoul, Republic of Korea

M.S. in Statistics (Applicational Statistics). Advisor: Dongwan Shin B.S. Major in Mathematics Education, Minor in Statistics

Graduated with Honors (Magna Cum Laude)

Mar. 2018 – Feb. 2020

Mar. 2014 – Feb. 2018

University of California, Davis

Exchange student in Mathematics

Davis, CA, USA Sep. 2015 – Feb. 2016

PUBLICATIONS

Conference and Journal Papers

[C7] QASA: Advanced Question Answering on Scientific Articles

Yoonjoo Lee*, Kyungjae Lee*, Sunghyun Park, Dasol Hwang, Jaehyeon Kim, Hong-in Lee, Moontae Lee *ICML 2023: Proceedings of the 40th International Conference on Machine Learning*

[C6] Cells, Generators, and Lenses: Design Framework for Object-Oriented Interaction with Large Language Models

Tae Soo Kim, Yoonjoo Lee, Minsuk Chang, Juho Kim

UIST 2023: Proceedings of the 2023 ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (to appear).

[C5] DAPIE: Interactive Step-by-Step Explanatory Dialogues to Answer Children's Why and How Questions

Yoonjoo Lee, Tae Soo Kim, Sundong Kim, Yohan Yun, Juho Kim

CHI 2023: Proceedings of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems.

[C4] Promptiverse: Scalable Generation of Scaffolding Prompts Through Human-AI Hybrid Knowledge Graph Annotation

Yoonjoo Lee, John Joon Young Chung, Tae Soo Kim, Jean Y. Song, Juho Kim

CHI 2022: Proceedings of the 2022 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems

[C3] Personalizing Ambience and Illusionary Presence: How People Use "Study with Me" Videos to Create Effective Studying Environments

Yoonjoo Lee, John Joon Young Chung, Jean Y. Song, Minsuk Chang, Juho Kim

CHI 2021: Proceedings of the 2021 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems.

[C2] A Machine Learning Approach that meets Axiomatic Properties in Probabilistic Analysis of LTE Spectral Efficiency

Yoonjoo Lee, Yunbae Kim, Seungken Park

ICTC, Oct. 2019

[C1] Probabilistic Analysis of Spectral Efficiency for LTE based on PDCCH Measurement Data

Yoonjoo Lee, Yunbae Kim, Yeonkyu Park, Seungken Park

IEEE Communications Letters, vol. 23, no. 9, Sep. 2019

Preprints

[A1] EvalLM: Interactive Evaluation of Large Language Model Prompts on User-Defined Criteria

Tae Soo Kim, Yoonjoo Lee, Jamin Shin, Young-Ho Kim, Juho Kim

Under Review, 2023

Posters and Workshop Papers

[P5] LMCanvas: Object-Oriented Interaction to Personalize Large Language Model-Powered Writing Environments

Tae Soo Kim, Arghya Sarkar, Yoonjoo Lee, Minsuk Chang, and Juho Kim

CHI 2023 Workshop on Generative AI and HCI

[P4] Interactive Children's Story Rewriting Through Parent-Children Interaction

Yoonjoo Lee, Tae Soo Kim, Minsuk Chang, Juho Kim

ACL 2022 Workshop on Intelligent and Interactive Writing Assistant

[P3] XDesign: Integrating Interface Design into Explainable AI Education

Hyungyu Shin, Nabila Sindi, Yoonjoo Lee, Jaeryoung Ka, Jean Y. Song, Juho Kim

SIGCSE TS 2022 Posters

[P2] A Study on the Distribution Analysis of LTE Resource Block Usage from TSME Measurement Data

Yoonjoo Lee, Yunbae Kim, Seungken Park

KICS, Jun. 2018

[P1] A Study on the Estimation of Probability Distribution of the Spectral Efficiency of LTE based on TSME Measurement Data

Yunbae Kim, Yoonjoo Lee, Seungken Park

KICS, Jun. 2018

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Allen Institute for AI (AI2)

Seattle, US

Research Scientist Intern, Semantic Scholar Team May - Oct. 2023

Mentor: Pao Siangliulue, Joseph Chee Chang, Jonathan Bragg, Kyle Lo

LG AI Research Seoul, Republic of Korea

Research Scientist Intern, Advanced Machine Learning Lab
Mentor: Moontae Lee, Kyungjae Lee

[C6]

KIXLAB, KAIST Daejeon, Republic of Korea

Graduate Research Intern

Mar. 2020 – Aug. 2020

Mentor: Juho Kim, Jean Y. Song

Electronics and Telecommunications Research Institute (ETRI)

Graduate Research Assistant, Data Sciences Group

Mentor: Yunbae Kim, Seungken Park [P1, P2, C1, C2]

Undergraduate Research Intern, Data Sciences Group Jan. 2018 – Feb. 2018

Mentor: Yunbae Kim, Seungken Park

Last Updated: November 3, 2023

Daejeon, Republic of Korea

Mar. 2018 – Dec. 2019

TEACHING

Introduction to Social Computing

KAIST CS473, Instructor: Juho Kim

Fall 2020, Fall 2021

Time Series Analysis

Regression Analysis

Ewha Womans University, Instructor: Dongwan Shin

Fall 2018

Spring 2019

Ewha Womans University, Instructor: Donghwan Lee

ACADEMIC SERVICES

Program Committee

• CHI LBW 2023

Reviewer

- EMNLP 2023
- CHI 2024, 2023, 2022
- UIST 2022, 2023
- ACL 2023
- CSCW 2023
- C&C 2022
- IEEE Transactions on Learning Technologies

Student Volunteer

CHI 2022

INVITED TALKS

Invited Talk at UCSD Design Lab

Oct. 2023

Title: Adapting Scaffolding to Support Knowledge Consumption through Interactive AI-Driven Systems

Invited Talk at University of Washington

Oct. 2023

Title: Adapting Scaffolding to Support Knowledge Consumption through Interactive AI-Driven Systems

HONORS, AWARDS, AND SCHOLARSHIPS

Research Assistant Scholarship

2019

College of Natural Sciences, Ewha Womans University

Admission Scholarship

2018

College of Natural Sciences, Ewha Womans University

Honors Scholarship

2014, 2015, 2016, 2017

College of Education, Ewha Womans University

Dean's List

2014, 2015, 2016, 2017

College of Education, Ewha Womans University

Ewha Womans University Alumnae Association Scholarship

College of Education, Ewha Womans University

SERVICE AND LEADERSHIP

KAIST-Google ExploreCSR

2022

2017

Student Organizer

Programming Mentoring

2016 - 2017

Leader of Student Organizer

HONORS, AWARDS, AND SCHOLARSHIPS

Research Assistant Scholarship

2019

College of Natural Sciences, Ewha Womans University

Admission Scholarship

2018

College of Natural Sciences, Ewha Womans University

Honors Scholarship

2014, 2015, 2016, 2017

College of Education, Ewha Womans University

Dean's List

2014, 2015, 2016, 2017

College of Education, Ewha Womans University

Ewha Womans University Alumnae Association Scholarship

2017

College of Education, Ewha Womans University

Electronics and Telecommunications Research Institute (ETRI)

Daejeon, Republic of Korea Feb. 2018 – May 2019

Research Assistant, Data Sciences Group

- Created applicable transformation making results follow approximately jointly normal distribution with measurement data
- Derived the key probabilities for SE analysis and adopted Deep Neural Network(DNN) to extend the analysis from measured cases to general cases.

Time Series Analysis Research Lab, Ewha Womans University

Seoul, Republic of Korea

Jan. 2019 - Dec. 2019

Time Series Research Lab (Advisor: Professor Dongwan Shin)

• Built prediction models for high frequency data

Probabilistic Analysis

Daejeon, Republic of Korea Feb. 2018 – May 2019

- Created applicable transformation making results follow approximately jointly normal distribution with measurement data
- Derived the key probabilities for SE analysis and adopted Deep Neural Network(DNN) to extend the analysis from measured cases to general cases.

Deep Learning

ETRI

Daejeon, Republic of Korea

Feb. 2018 - Dec. 2018

• Participated in research on busy hour RB usage rates data

- Stochastic modeling: Derived a method to estimate probability density of the data by the family of Exponentialed Exponential Distribution using quantiles
- Deep Learning: Predicted future RBU using Long Short-Term Memory(LSTM), Gated Recurrent Unit(GRU), Encoder-Decoder versions models

Time Series Analysis

Seoul, Republic of Korea

Jan. 2019 – Dec. 2019

Time Series Research Lab (Advisor: Professor Dongwan Shin)

- Built prediction models for high frequency data
 - Deep Learning: Used DNN, LSTM for Realized Volatility(RV) classification and regression
 - Time Series model: Used Autoregressive Integrated Moving Average(ARIMA) and Heterogeneous Autoregressive(HAR) model to forecast RV and compared with Deep Learning model based on prediction error
- Applied dimension reduction methods to simplify original data structure with 40 financial features and forecast future RV

KAIST-Google ExploreCSR

Spring 2022 – Present

Student Organizer

Programming Mentoring

Mar. 2016 - Dec. 2017

Leader of Student Organizer

• Planned and led lectures about Python and Ruby on Rails for college students, prepared learning materials including lecture

slides and coding assignments

• Organized a Hackathon event for 100+ students to promote cooperation with students from other schools

Mathematics Mentoring in Ewha Girl's High School, Seoul, South Korea

• Taught math to high school students every week with follow-up Q&A sessions

Feb. 2015 – Dec. 2017

ACADEMIC SERVICES

Reviewer

CHI 2022

C&C 2022

IEEE Transactions on Learning Technologies

Student Volunteer

CHI 2022

SERVICE AND LEADERSHIP

KAIST-Google ExploreCSR

Spring 2022 - Present

Student Organizer

Programming Mentoring

Mar. 2016 - Dec. 2017

Leader of Student Organizer

Mathematics Mentoring in Ewha Girl's High School

Feb. 2015 – Dec. 2017

Mentor

My research interest is supporting people to perform tasks ranging from teaching, writing, to prototyping effectively by 1) building AI powered systems with humans in the loop and 2) analyzing and adapting large scale data and models. Specifically, one of my research goals is to create computational methods and systems that support scalable teaching and learning using human-AI collaboration.